A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 2010-2013
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 2010-2013
The Library of Virginia
51126
6.3 cu.ft. (18 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected information is considered closed for 75 years after date of record creation. Types of records restricted include but are not limited to: Attorney-client privilege materials and social security numbers. Restricted information has been sealed, but has not been removed from the collection.
Acquisition Information
Transferred on 8 January 2014 by the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 1111 East Broad Street, Room 4095, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
Historical Information
Finally established in 2004, the eventual creation of the Agriculture and Forestry secretariat began with a 2001 gubernatorial campaign promise made by Governor Mark R. Warner to provide cabinet level representation for the agriculture and forestry industry. Further support for the creation of the secretariat came from the Governor's Agriculture Net Receipts Work Group, a task force created in 2003 by Governor Warner through the Secretary of Commerce and Trade. The goal of the task force was to determine strategies and recommendations for doubling the net profits of Virginia's agricultural sector between 2004 and 2014. Among the task force's recommendations was the creation of the, "Office of Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry to provide focus and emphasis in the development of the agriculture and forest industries." In 2004, the General Assembly of Virginia created the cabinet position of Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry with the passing of Senate Bill SB 543 and witnessed its codification through 2.2-203.3 of the Code of Virginia. Speaking at the appointment ceremony of the first Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, Governor Warner reiterated his commitment to, "support and expand our agriculture and forestry industries" and recalled his desire to, "make sure these very important sectors of Virginia's economy received a seat at my cabinet table."
The Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry is appointed by the Governor, confirmed by the General Assembly, and serves at the Governor's pleasure. It is the secretary's responsibility to oversee several agencies and other entities that formerly reported to the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade. Among the agencies reporting to the Agriculture and Forestry secretariat are the Virginia Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services, the Department of Forestry, the Virginia Agricultural Council, and the Virginia Marine Products Board. The Governor may assign or reassign agencies to and from the Agriculture and Forestry secretariat through the use of executive orders. The secretary's role in leading agencies within the Agriculture and Forestry secretariat is to provide guidance and direction, "in the conservation, protection, and development of Virginia's agricultural and forest resources and in protecting the Virginia Consumer."
Governor Robert F. McDonnell appointed Todd Haymore to serve as the Virginia Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry in 2010 and he served until September 2016.
Scope and Content
Records, 2010-2013, created and maintained by Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, Todd Haymore, during the administration of Governor Robert F, McDonnell (2010-2014). The records include agendas, correspondence, memorandum, newspaper clippings, presentations, programs, reports, speeches, studies, and other working papers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Board and Commission Meetings, 2005-2013
Series II: Cabinet Meetings, 2010-2012
Series III: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Assigned State Agencies, 2010-2014
Series IV: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Office of the Secretary, Events and Speeches, 2010-2013
Series V: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Office of the Secretary, Subject files, 2010-2014
Contents List
- Series I: Board and Commission Meetings, 2005-2013., Extent: 3 boxes (1.05 cu. ft.). (Box 1-3)
  Series I: Board and Commission Meetings, 2005-2013, is housed in 3 boxes and arranged alphabetically by folder title. This series includes agendas, correspondence, financial records, minutes, presentations, and studies from Boards and Commissions in which the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry involved. Boards include the Chesapeake Bay Executive Council, VEDP Board, Virginia Horse Center Foundation Board, Virginia Tobacco Commission, and Virginia Wine Board, among others.
  - Agriculture and Comsumer Services, Board Meeting, 2013 December 5. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ayshire Farm (Loudoun County, Va.), 2009. (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Chesapeake Bay, Executive Council Meeting, 2011 July 11. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - National Grape and Wine Initiative, Board Meeting, 2010 October 25. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Old Dominion Agriculture Foundation, Inc., 2010-2011. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pittsylvania County Agricultural Complex, 2008. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rural Jobs Council, 2013. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Rural Rehabilitation Trust Fund, 2005-2009. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - State Fair of Virginia, 2008-2009. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership (VEDP), Board Meeting, 2012 September 13. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership (VEDP), Board Meeting, 2012 December 13. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership (VEDP), Board Meeting, 2013 March 14. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership (VEDP), Board Meeting, 2013 June 13. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Horse Center Foundation, Board Meeting, 2010 January 20. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Horse Center Foundation, Board of Directors, 2007-2009. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Horse Center Foundation, Proposal, 2008. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Tech Charitable Purposes Board, Meetings, 2009. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Tobacco Commission, Meeting, 2010 October 27-28. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Tobacco Commission, Meeting, 2011 January 10-11. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Tourism Corporation, Meeting, 2010 October 4. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Wine Board, Meeting, 2010 December 6. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Wine Board, Meeting, 2013 March 18-19. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Wine Board, Meeting, 2013 June 4. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Wine Board, Meeting, 2013 August 21. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Wine Board, Meeting, 2013 December 4. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Wine Board, Meeting, Undated. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Winery Distribution Company, Meeting, 2007 August 30. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series II: Cabinet Meetings, 2010-2012., Extent: 2 1/2 boxes (.90 cu. ft.). (Box 4-6)
  Series II: Cabinet Meetings, 2010-2012, is housed in 2 1/2 boxes and arranged chronologically. This series contains records relating to Secretary Todd Haymore's participation in Governor Robert F. McDonnell's cabinet meetings. Records in this series include cabinet meeting schedules annotated by Secretary Haymore, weekly reports of the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, and notes on topics to be discussed with Commonwealth policymakers both during cabinet meetings and afterwards. Topics of particular interest in this series include international trade, Virginia wineries, and requests by Virginia localities for disaster designation due to drought conditions.
  - Cabinet Meeting, Retreat, 2010 January 7-8. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Cabinet Meeting, 2010 January-March. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Cabinet Meeting, 2010 April-May. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Cabinet Meeting, 2010 June-September. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cabinet Meeting, 2010 October-December. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Cabinet Meeting, 2011 January-March. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cabinet Meeting, 2011 April-June. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Cabinet Meeting, 2011 July-September. (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Cabinet Meeting, 2011 October-November. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Cabinet Meeting, Retreat, 2011 October 10-11. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Cabinet Meeting, 2012 January-February. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Series III: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Assigned State Agencies,, 2009-2013., Extent: 2 boxes (.70 cu. ft.). (Box 6-8)
  Series III: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Assigned State Agencies, 2009-2013, is housed in 2 boxes and arranged alphabetically by folder title. This series contains information on the budget, House and Senate Bills, and correspondence.
  - AFID (Agriculture and Forestry Industries Development Fund), General, 2012. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - AFID, Homestead Creamery, nd. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - AFID, Red Sun Farms, 2013. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - AFID, Virginia Produce, 2013. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Budget, 2011-2012. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, General, 2010. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Constituent, 2010 February-April. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Constituent, 2010 May-June. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, General, 2011. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, General, 2013. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Dept. of Forestry, Manassas, 2011. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Enrolled Bill reviews, 2010. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Executive Amendments to the 2010-2012 Biennial Budget, 2010. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Governor's Amendments, Talking Points HOuse Version, 2013. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - House Bills, 2009. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - House Bills, 2010. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - House Bills, Comments, 2010. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Legislative Action Summary, 2011. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Legislative Action Summary, 2012. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Senate Bills, 2009. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Senate Bills, 2010. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Senate Bills, Comments, 2010. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Senate Finance, 2011. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Senate Finance, 2012. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Wine-Vine Tax Credit (HB 1194), 2012. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Office of the Secretary, Events and Speeches,, 2010-2013., Extent: 5 boxes (1.75 cu. ft.). (Box 8-12)
  Series IV: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Office of the Secretary, Events and Speeches, 2010-2013, is housed in 5 boxes and arranged chronologically. This series includes brochures, correspondence, event briefing information, minutes, newspaper clippings, notes, presentations, press releases, and other sundry materials. Of note are copies of speeches given at the events by Secretary Todd Haymore and talking points for Governor Robert F. McDonnell.
  - SunTrust Governor's Cup Gala, 2010 February 26. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Agricultural Trade-International Trade Workshop Conference, 2010 March 3-4. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Vineyards Association, 2010 March 5. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Agroterrorism Conference, 2010 March 23. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - VDACS, Eastern Shore Seafood Packing Facility, 2010 May 5. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Williamsburg Land Conservancy Farm to Fork Dinner, 2010 August 22. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Agriculture Conference, 2010 August 24. (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Governor's Retreat, 2010 September 18-19. (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - "Vintage" screening, 2010 September 22. (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - The Homeplace Vineyard, 2010 September 24. (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Wine Month Event at Monticello, 2010 September 29. (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - State Fair of Virginia Breakfast, 2010 October 1. (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - NYC-VTC Taste of Virginia, 2010 October 19-20. (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Wine Liter Tax Bill signing, 2010 October 22. (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - SODRA Meeting, 2010 November 22. (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Wednesday Club, 2010 December 1. (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Agriculture and Forestry, Accomplishments, 2010. (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Wine Law Seminar, 2011 January 31. (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Rural Caucus, 2011 February. (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Virginia Vineyards Association, 2011 February 17-19. (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Southwest Virginia Agricultural Association, 2011 March 5. (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - NACUFS (National Association of College and University Food Services), Mid-Atlantic Region Conference, 2011 March 6-9. (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Viticulture Wine Society, 2011 March 11. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - International Trade Workshop, 2011 March 16. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Agribusiness Council, 2011 March 21. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Wineries Unlimited Trade Show and Conference, 2011 March 19-April 1. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Poultry Health and Management Seminar, 2011 April 12. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Citizens for a Better Eastern Shore, 2011 April 13. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - National Governor's Association, 2011 July 15-17. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Hurricane Irene, 2011 August 30. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Vine to Wine Event, 2011 August 31. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Trump Vineyard Estates Opening, 2011 October 4. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Governors Cabinet Exercise, 2011 October 24. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Sorensen Institute (UVA), 2011 October 24. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Wine Month Reception, 2011 October 26. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - VDACS, Robert S. Bloxom Agricultural Complex, 2011 October 27. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Agribusiness Council, 2011 October 31. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Farm Bureau Federation Annual Conference, 2011 November 30. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Universal Leaf, 20101 December 9. (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Farmland Preservation Workshop, 2011 December 13. (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Circle of Wine Event, 2011 December. (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Governor's Cup, 2011. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Tobacco Workers Conference, 2012 January 16-19. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Soybean Association, 2012 February 23. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Fibro Virginia Project, 2012 February. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Wine Industry, Economic Impact Study, 2012 February. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Vineyard Association, 2012 February. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Wine America Conference, 2012 March 12. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Beach Excellence in Agriculture, 2012 March 15. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Wine Region Signs, 2012 April. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Fauquier County, 2012 July 12. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Enviva LP Ground breaking, 2012 July 25. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Executive Mansion Bicentennial Virginia Wine Program, 2012 August 2. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - South Hill Tobacco Associates Tour, 2012 August 24. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - "Spotlight on Agriculture," 2012 August 26. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Jefferson Innovation Summit for the Commonwealth, 2012 September 7. (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Governor's Cabinet Retreat, 2012 September 16-17. (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Agriculture Leaders Obtaining Results (VALOR), 2012 September. (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Virginia Wine Summit, 2012 October 2. (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - VBA Corporate Counsel, 2012 October 16. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Terroir and Merroir, 2012 November 9-11. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - National Thanksgiving Turkey Send Off, 2012 November 19. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Farm Bureau Federation Annual Convention, 2012 November 27. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Agricultural Exports, Op-Ed, 2012. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Perdue Agri Business, Port plans, 2012-2013. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Grains and Soybean Conference, 2013 February 29. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Greencore Group, 2013 March 25. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Danville-Pittsylvania County Chamber of Commerce, 2013 March 27. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Enviva, 2013 April 30. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Maritime Association, 2013 May 9. (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Poultry Health and Management Seminar, 2013 May 15. (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Congressional Staff Delegation Tour, 2013 May 29-31. (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Fairfax Committee of 100, 2013 June 3. (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Homestead Retreat, 2013 June 13-15. (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Smithfield Meeting, 2013 June 18. (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - L.D. Amory Co. and Graham & Rollins Press Conference, 2013 June 26. (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Fancy Food Show, 2013 June 30-July 2. (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Beyond 2015: Virginia Wine Strategic Planning Retreat, 2013 July 10. (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Blue Bee Cider Grand Opening, 2013 July 11. (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - North American Agricultural Marketing Officers (NAAMO) Conference, 2013 July 17. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - National Council Forest Association Executives (NCFAAE)/Forest Industry Association Council (FIAC) Annual meeting, 2013 July 24-26. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Central Virginia Spotlight on Agriculture, 2013 July 25. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Governor's Statewide Tour, 2013 August 10-16. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Valley Business Summit, 2013 August 12. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Agribuiness Council (VAC) Roundtable, 2013 August 21. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Gleaning Day, 2013 August 22. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - VAC Town Hall Meeting 2013 August 26. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Roy Seward Retirement and Reception, 2013 August 30. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - NASA Develop National Program, 2013 Summer. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Danville Agribusiness Roundtable, 2013 September 4. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Rogers' Banana Pudding Sauce Grand Opening, 2013 September 5. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - CSX-Quintin Kendall Meeting, 2013 September 5. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Consul General of Japan, 2013 September 9. (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Integrated Aquaculture Meeting, 2013 September 9. (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Altavista Power Station Rededication, 2013 September 12. (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Produce Company AFID Announcement, 2013 September 25. (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - International Agribusiness Conference, 2013 September 25-26. (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Racing to Richmond with Danny Marshall, 2013 September 26=27. (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - October Virginia Wine Month, 2013 September 30. (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Internal Audit of Livestock Marketing Services, 2013 September. (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Enology/Viticulture Center, 2013 October 3. (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Food for Thought Ground breaking Ceremony, 2013 October 15. (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - WVTP Interview, 2013 October 10. (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Landes Meeting, 2013 October 10. (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - VAC Shenandoah Regional Roundtable, 2013 October 10. (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - VCU Food Day, 2013 October 23. (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Kickoff for Wine Summit, 2013 October 27. (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Cider Week, 2013 November 18. (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Virginia Ag Development Officers (VADO) Meeting, 2013 November 19. (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - International Paper, 2013 November 19. (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - Virginia Free Annual Meeting, 2013 December 10. (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Pilot Op-Ed Exports, 2013. (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - ,. (Box 13)
  - ,. (Box 13)
- Series V: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Office of the Secretary, Subject files,, 2010-2013., Extent: 5 boxes (1.75 cu. ft.). (Box 13-)
  Series V: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Office of the Secretary, Subject files, 2010-2013, is housed in 5 boxes and arranged chronologically.
  - ,. (Box 13)